Dr. Sara Pérez Vieites

sara.perez-vieites@imt-nord-europe.fr > Google scholar profile > sarapv.github.io

RESEARCH PROFILE

I am a postdoctoral researcher at the CERI Systèmes Numériques (Digital Systems) of IMT Nord Europe, where I am carrying out research in computational statistics under the supervision of Dr. Víctor Elvira (University of Edinburgh). More specifically, I am interested in Bayesian inference, parameter estimation, filtering techniques and their application to different fields of science (e.g., engineering, ecology, meteorology, etc.).

I completed the Ph.D. in Statistical Signal Processing from Universidad Carlos III of Madrid in 2022, under the supervision of Dr. Joaquín Míguez. My novel research has been published in two journals of different disciplines and in three well-known peer-reviewed signal processing conferences. I have presented all my research advances in nine international and two national conferences.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Visiting Researcher Jan. 2023 - Present

School of Mathematics, University of Edinburgh (Edinburgh, UK)

Postdoctoral Researcher Sept. 2022 - Present

CERI Systèmes Numériques, IMT Nord Europe (Villeneuve-d'Ascq, France)

Research Assistant Dec. 2016 - May 2022

Department of Signal Theory & Communications, University Carlos III of Madrid (Madrid, Spain)

Apr. 2019 - July 2019 PhD internship

Department of Mathematics and Statistics, University of Reading (Reading, UK)

Research collaboration/visit Jan. 2019

MeteoGalicia (Santiago de Compostela, Spain)

Research collaboration/visit July 2018

Centre Tecnològic de Telecomunicacions de Catalunya (CTTC, in Barcelona, Spain)

June 2015 - Aug. 2015

Gradiant, Technology Centre of Telecommunications of Galicia (Vigo, Spain)

Trainee June 2014 - Aug. 2014

R Cable y Telecomunicaciones, S.A. (A Coruña, Spain)

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Statistical Signal Processing

Title: Nested filtering methods for Bayesian inference in state space models

Supervisor: Joaquín Míguez Arenas

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid (Spain)

Description: Development of Bayesian filtering methods, from a practical en theoretical point of view, in order

Sept. 2017 - Jan. 2022

Sept. 2015 - Sept. 2017

to perform accurate parameter estimation and prediction of time- varying high-dimensional systems.

Master's Degree in Telecommunications Engineering

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid (Spain)

Master's Degree in Multimedia and Communications Sept. 2015 - July 2017

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid (Spain)

Description: Master specialised in topics such as machine learning, computer vision and signal processing.

Bachelor's Degree in Telecommunication Technologies Engineering Sept. 2011 - June 2015

Universidade de Vigo (Spain)

Description: Specialisation in Sound and Image.

LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

My research has been published in two journals of different disciplines and in three well-known peer-reviewed signal processing conferences/workshops.

Journal papers:

- J2. Pérez-Vieites, S., & Míguez, J. (2021). *Nested Gaussian filters for recursive Bayesian inference and nonlinear tracking in state space models.* Signal Processing, 189, 108295.
- J1. Pérez-Vieites, S., Mariño, I. P., & Míguez, J. (2018). *Probabilistic scheme for joint parameter estimation and state prediction in complex dynamical systems.* Physical Review E, 98(6), 063305.

Conference peer-reviewed papers:

- C4. Pérez-Vieites, S., & Elvira, V. (2023). Adaptive Gaussian nested filter for parameter estimation and state tracking in dynamical systems. In ICASSP 2023 [Accepted paper].
- C3. Pérez-Vieites, S., & Míguez, J. (2020). *A nested hybrid filter for parameter estimation and state tracking in homogeneous multi-scale models.* In 2020 IEEE 23rd International Conference on Information Fusion (FUSION) (pp. 1-8). IEEE.
- C2. Pérez-Vieites, S., & Míguez, J. (2020). *Kalman-based nested hybrid filters for recursive inference in state-space models.* In 2020 28th European Signal Processing Conference (EUSIPCO) (pp. 2468- 2472). IEEE.
- C1. Pérez-Vieites, S., Vilà-Vals, J., Bugallo, M. F., Míguez, J., & Closas, P. (2019). Second Order Subspace Statistics for Adaptive State-Space Partitioning in Multiple Particle Filtering. In 2019 IEEE 8th Intenational Workshop on Computational Advances in Multi-Sensor Adaptive Processing (CAMSAP) (pp. 609-613). IEEE.

Pre-prints and submitted papers:

• Pérez-Vieites, S., Molina-Bulla, H., & Míguez, J. (2022). *Nested smoothing algorithms for inference and tracking of heterogeneous multi-scale state-space systems.* arXiv preprint arXiv:2204.07795.

FELLOWSHIPS, GRANTS, PRIZES AND AWARDS

Submission to MSCA Postdoctoral Fellowship Assessment in progress Submission to EPSRC Open Postdoc Fellowship Assessment in progress Runner up poster presentation SIAM-IMA student chapter conference, University of Reading (Reading, UK) PIPF grant (Personal Pre-doctoral en Formación) for Ph.D. students Universidad Carlos III de Madrid (Madrid, Spain)

ORGANISATION ACTIVITIES

Support activities in the MSc Earth Observation Challenge 2023	20/02/2023 - 23/02/2023
Organised by Saxavord and the University of Edinburgh.	

Local arrangements committee, SMC 2022

I have been involved in the organisation of the 5th Workshop in Sequential Monte Carlo Methods 2022 (SMC 2022) in Madrid, Spain. To be specific, I led the **local arrangements committee**, producing the programme, arranging the registration materials, and supporting the sessions.

04/05/2022 - 06/05/2022

Statistics Seminar, School of Mathematics, University of Edinburgh.

27/02/2023

Title: Nested filtering methods for Bayesian inference in state space models

CONFERENCES AND SUMMER SCHOOLS

I have presented all my research advances in nine international and two national conferences. I have also attended other workshops and summer schools.

SIAM Conference on Mathematics of Data Science (MDS22)

26/09/2022 - 30/09/2022

Hybrid conference. San Diego, California (US)

Attendance and poster presentation

• 5th Workshop in Sequential Monte Carlo Methods 2022 (SMC 2022)

04/05/2022 - 06/05/2022

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid (Spain)

Attendance and poster presentation

Part of the local arrangements committee

• 9th Spanish Workshop on Signal Proc., Communications & Inf. Theory (SIC 2022)

03/05/2022

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid (Spain) Attendance and poster presentation

• 28th European Signal Processing Conference (EUSIPCO 2020)

18/01/2021 - 22/01/2021

Virtual conference

Attendance and poster presentation

Paper title: Kalman-based nested hybrid filters for recursive inference in state-space models.

• 23rd Conference on Information Fusion (FUSION 2020)

06/07/2020 - 09/07/2020

Virtual conference

Attendance and poster presentation

Paper title: A nested hybrid filter for parameter estimation and state tracking in homogeneous multi-scale models.

• 27th European Signal Processing Conference (EUSIPCO 2019)

02/09/2019 - 07/09/2019

Universidade de A Coruña (Spain)

Attendance and 3 minutes thesis talk

Workshop on Stochastic Parametrizations & Their Use in Data Assimilation 01/07/2019 - 05/07/2019
 Imperial College London (UK)

Attendance

Mathematics of Planet Earth Centre for Doctoral Training Summer School 24/06/2019 - 28/06/2019
 Met Office (Exeter, UK)

Attendance

SIAM-IAM student chapter conference

07/06/2019

University of Reading (UK)

Attendance and poster presentation

LMS Invited Lecture Series & CRISM Summer School in Comp. Statistics 09/06/2018 - 13/06/2018
 Warwick University (UK)

Attendance and poster presentation

ISBA 2018 World Meeting

24/06/2018 - 29/06/2018

University of Edinburgh (UK)

Attendance and poster presentation

Particle methods and Data assimilation workshop

Imperial College London (UK)

Attendance

• 7th Spanish Workshop on Signal Proc., Inf. Theory & Communications

23/01/2018

Universidad de Navarra (San Sebastián, Spain)

Attendance and poster presentation

Sequential Monte Carlo Workshop 2017 (SMC 2017)

30/08/2017 - 01/09/2017

08/05/2018 - 10/05/2018

Uppsala University (Sweden)

Attendance and poster presentation

PROJECTS

I have participated in the following research projects at Universidad Carlos III as part of the scientific team.

 PRACTICO-CM Psiquiatría Computacional y Modelos Integrales de Comportamiento Funding agency: CAM. Consejería de Educación e Investigación (Y2018/TCS-4705)
 PI: Antonio Artés Rodríguez

 BAYTREE Advanced Bayesian computation methods for modelling and inference in complex dynamical networks

Funding agency: Office of Naval Research Global (N00014-18-S-B001)

PI: Joaquín Míguez Arenas

 Métodos computacionales bayesianos avanzados para estimación, predicción y control en sistemas multisensoriales complejos

Funding agency: Ministerio de asuntos económicos y transformación digital (TEC2015-69868-C2- 1-R) PI: Antonio Artés Rodríguez, Joaquín Míguez Arenas

 NICOP - a new sequential Monte Carlo framework for tracking of non-linear complex dynamical systems
 Funding agency: Office of Naval Research Global (N62909-15-1-2011)
 PI: Joaquín Míguez Arenas

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

I have taken part in the teaching duties at undergraduate level, teaching (in Spanish and/or English) different courses in telecommunications engineering. I have also obtained good teaching quality indicators.

Courses taught at Universidad Carlos III as teaching assistant:

• Linear systems (2017-2019)

<u>Degrees:</u> Mobile and Space Communications Engineering (B.Sc.), Telecommunication Technologies Engineering (B.Sc.) and Telematics Engineering (B.Sc.)

Teaching hours: 112 hours

Linear networks analysis and synthesis (2017 – 2018)

Degree: Telecommunication Technologies Engineering (B.Sc.)

Teaching hours: 5 hours

At Universidad Carlos III, detailed polls are anonymously filled by students at the end of each course. All the grades obtained have been averaged over all courses and all academic years yielding: **4.1/5**.

OUTREACH ACTIVITIES

 I have established a collaboration with MeteoGalicia, a meteorological centre (equivalent to the MetOffice in Galicia region, Spain), to apply stochastic filtering in weather forecasting. I have used the Weather Research and Forecasting (WRF) Model and data collected from meteorological base stations in Galicia. • Participation in the **three minutes thesis (3MT)** at EUSIPCO 2019. Qualified as a finalist. Here I had to present a compelling oration on my thesis and its significance to an audience specialised in different areas.

REVIEWER ACTIVITIES

I have served as reviewer for several journals and conferences.

• **Journals:** Foundations of Data Science, IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing, and IEEE Signal Processing Letters.

• Conferences: EUSIPCO.

MAJOR COLLABORATIONS

I have started several collaborations with other six researchers from different research areas and universities.

• Inés Pérez Mariño (Professor at the Universidad Juan Carlos, Spain).

Research area: Applied Physics.

Description: We investigated the use of Bayesian inference methods in chaotic and nonlinear systems.

• Jochen Broecker (Associate Professor at the University of Reading, UK).

Research area: Statistics.

Description: Analysis of different stochastic parameterisations and how they affect the behaviour of simplified models.

 Jordi Vilà-Valls (Associate Professor at ISAE-SUPAERO, University of Toulouse, France), Pau Closas (Assistant Professor at Northeastern University, USA), Mónica F. Bugallo (Professor at Stony Brook University, USA) and Petar M. Djurić (Distinguished Professor at Stony Brook University, USA).

Research area: Electrical and Computer Engineering.

<u>Description:</u> We have investigated the use of Bayesian methods in engineering challenges such as multiple target tracking and estimation of high-dimensional systems.

LANGUAGES

English Professional level Intermediate level Spanish Native speaker Native speaker